Clara Lacroce

Personal Profile

I am a mathematician with a PhD in Machine Learning and Al. During my PhD and postdoc, I investigated the learning capabilities of deep sequence models and their connections with formal language theory and functional analysis. I am a fast learner with experience in problem solving, data analysis and project management. Pursuing Data Science and Consulting opportunities.

Education

McGill University

Montréal, Canada

PhD in Computer Science

2016 - 2022

- Thesis: The approximate minimization problem of weighted finite automata and applications to language modelling: an approach based on Adamyan-Arov-Krein theory.
- Supervisors: Prakash Panangaden, Doina Precup.

Concordia University Montréal, Canada

MSc in Mathematics, ALGANT Erasmus Mundus

2015 - 2016

- Thesis: Deformations of Galois Representations.
- · Supervisor: Adrian Iovita.

Università degli Study di Padova

Padova, Italy

Master in Mathematics, ALGANT Erasmus Mundus

2014 - 2016

• Specialization: Algebra, Geometry, Number Theory

BSc in Mathematics 2010 - 2014

Work Experience

McGill University

Montréal, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher 2022 - 2023

- Investigated the learning capabilities of deep sequence models and connections with models from formal language theory.
- Co-led the efforts and mentored the work of 3 graduate student on .

Teaching Assistant 2017 - 2020

• Led tutorials and Q&A sessions with 50 students.

Université Jean Monnet Saint-Étienne, France

Invited Visiting Researcher

2023

• Funded to work for a month at Laboratoire Hubert Curien

University of Padova, Board of Directors

Padova, Italy

Student Representative, BofD

2015

• Advocated for students needs, elected to represent \sim 60K students.

Selected Publications

Optimal Approximate Minimization of One-Letter Irredundant WFAs

Clara Lacroce*, Borja Balle, Prakash Panangaden and Guillaume Rabusseau

Under review in the Journal Mathematical Structure in Computer Science (2023). 2023

Length independent PAC-Bayes bound for saturated Simple RNNs

Volodimir Mitarchuck* and Clara Lacroce and Remi Emonet and Remi Eyraud and Amaury Habrard and Guillaume Rabusseau Under review at NEURIPS (2023), 2023

The approximate minimization problem of weighted finite automata and applications to language modelling: an approach based on Adamyan-Arov-Krein theory

Clara Lacroce

McGill University (2022). 2022

Towards an AAK Theory Approach to Approximate Minimization in the Multi-Letter Case

Clara Lacroce*, Prakash Panangaden and Guillaume Rabusseau

CoRR abs/2206.00172 (2022). 2022

Extracting Weighted Automata for Approximate Minimization in Language Modelling

Clara Lacroce*, Prakash Panangaden and Guillaume Rabusseau

Proceedings of the Fifteenth International Conference on Grammatical Inference, 2021

Optimal Spectral-Norm Approximate Minimization of Weighted Finite Automata

Borja Balle and Clara Lacroce* and Prakash Panangaden and Doina Precup and Guillaume Rabusseau

48th International Colloquium on Automata, Languages, and Programming, ICALP 2021, July 12-16, 2021, Glasgow, Scotland (Virtual Conference), 2021

Awards

Outstanding Teaching Assistant AwardMcGill University2019Graduate Excellence AwardMcGill University2017 - 2018Cryptoworks21 ScholarshipNSERC (Declined)2016 - 2017Armand C. Archambault FellowshipConcordia University2016International ALGANT AwardAlgant Consortium2015 - 2016

Selected Invited Talks

The approximate minimization problem of weighted finite automata and applications to language modelling: an approach based on Adamyan-Arov-Krein theory

•	Laboratoire Hubert Curien, Université Jean Monnet, Saint-Etienne	2023
•	Workshop Algorithmic aspects of dynamical systems, Barbados	2023
•	Seminar on Formal Languages and Neural Networks (FLaNN), online	2022

Optimal Spectral-Norm Approximate Minimization

•	• QUALOG 2023, Boston	2023
	• ICALP 2021, online	2021
	Online Worldwide Seminar on Logic and Semantics. Cambridge	2021

Towards an AAK Theory Approach to Approximate Minimization in the Multi-Letter Case

• LEARNAUT 2022, Paris 2022

Extracting Weighted Automata for Approximate Minimization in Language Modelling

• ICGI 2020-2021, online 2021

Community Service

Reviewer	Mathematical Structures in Computer Science, AISTATS2023, ICGI2023.	2022 - Current
Surgical Floor Volunteer	Montréal Children Hospital. Provided relief for babies post surgery.	2019 - 2022
CPE Child Educator	CPE Childcare, McGill, Montréal. Supervised 12 toddlers.	2017 - 2019
Mentor	Collegio Mazza, Padova. Advised a group of women in their freshman year.	2013 - 2015

Skills_

Programming	Python, Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-learn.
Software/OS	Git. Matlab. Unix. MEX. Microsoft Office.

Languages_

English	Full	prof	essional	prof	ficiency.	
---------	------	------	----------	------	-----------	--

French Professional working proficiency (TEFAQ: Listening C2, Speaking C1)

Italian Native proficiency.

^{*} Corresponding author.